Alfred Leyburn Papers WLU.Coll.0098
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Alfred Leyburn Papers
1823-1899
1830-01-01-1839-01-01
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Leyburn, Alfred
Leyburn, Edward J.
Junkin, Marion Montague
WLU.Coll.0098
.2 Linear Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Marion Junkin in 1979.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Alfred Leyburn attended Washington College (Va.), 1821-1822; practiced as a physician in Lexington, Va., was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1835 – 36, 1838 – 1842, and 1852, was a member of the Board of Visitors of the Virginia Military Institute, 1839 – 46, and served as rector and member of the Washington College and Washington and Lee University Board of Trustees, 1840-1878.
Scope and Contents
Contains c.55 items, of Dr. Alfred Leyburn and the Leyburn family of Lexington, Va., including 22 letters between Leyburn and his wife, Ann Eliza, 1835-36; patents of Edward J. Leyburn.
Patents; Correspondence; Caruthers, William Alexander; Leyburn, Ann Eliza; Leyburn, Edward J.; Washington and Lee University. Trustees --: History; Junkin, Marion Montague
- Letter by Levi H. McLean to James Kerr, 1823; McLean, Levi H.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  McLean writes about concern for Kerr's health, studies, etc. He also mentions their acquaintences and comments on their activities.
  Correspondence; Kerr, James
- Letters from George Leyburn, Edward Caruthers, and George C. Bagby, 1832-1834; Leyburn, George; Bagby, George C.; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This file includes two letters from George Leyburn: one to Ann Eliza, 1832, and one to Alfred, 1832. One letter is from Edward Caruthers to Ann Eliza, 1834, and one is from George C. Bagby to Alred, 1834. The last sent from Canyton, Ky., to Ann Eliza, 1833, but part of the letter is missing and the sender is unidentified.
  Leyburn, Ann Eliza; Leyburn, Alfred; Caruthers, Edward
- Letter from M. Jane to Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1835; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  "M. Jane," most likely Mary Jane (see letter from James) addresses Ann Eliza as "Grandmair" and discusses family and social affairs, weather, and gossip.
  Correspondence; Gossip; Leyburn, Ann Eliza
- Letter from James to Ann Eliza, 1835; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  "James" is most likely the sister of "M. Jane." He addresses Ann Eliza as "Grandma" and mentions Mary Jane.
  Correspondence; Leyburn, Ann Eliza
- Letter from Edward "Ned" Caruthers to Ann Eliza, 1835; Caruthers, Edward; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Edward discusses his social life, business, food, and Washington College.
- Correspondence Between Alfred and Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1835-12; Leyburn, Alfred; 6 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Alfred writes about his activities attending the legislature and answers her questions about matters in Lexington. Ann Eliza writes about Alfred coming home for Christmas, the slaves, cooking, social life, and their animals.
- Letter from Dr. William A. Caruthers to Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1835-12; Caruthers, William Alexander; 7 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
  William writes of Mrs. Calhoun's activities, his medical work, prices of goods, and business opportunities.
- Correspondences Between Alfred and Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1836-01; Leyburn, Alfred; Leyburn, Ann Eliza; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondences Between Alfred and Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1836-02; Leyburn, Alfred; Leyburn, Ann Eliza; 6 Item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence
- Letter from John E. Lewis to Ann Eliza, 1836-02; Lewis, John E.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  John addresses Ann Eliza as "Mother" and writes of his activities, sermons, etc.
- Correspondences Between Alfred and Ann Eliza Leyburn, 1836-03; Leyburn, Alfred; Leyburn, Ann Eliza; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter from John E. Lewis to Ann Eliza, 1836-03; Lewis, John E.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter from Dr. William A. Caruthers to Ann Eliza, 1836-07; Caruthers, William Alexander; Caruthers, Louisa; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 9)
  William Caruthers (and his wife Louisa) writes to Ann Eliza about his life and medical practice in Kanawha, Va.
- Letter from Dr. H.W. Moseley to Alfred, 1836-07; Moseley, H. W., Dr.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Dr. H.W. Moseley (Ann Eliza's brother-in-law) writes to Alfred about Ann Eliza's health.
  Correspondence; Leyburn, Ann Eliza; Leyburn, Alfred
- Letter from William Leyburn to Alfred and Ann Pope Leyburn, 1839-12-03; Leyburn, William; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 10)
  William Leyburn writes to his father and step-mother about school, health, and activities.
  Correspondence; Leyburn, Alfred; Leyburn, Ann Pope
- Letter from Edward Leyburn to Alfred and Ann Leyburn, 1841; Leyburn, Edward J.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Edwards writes from Brownsburg about school, etc.
- Letter from Mary Leyburn Junkin, 1899-07-04; Junkin, Mary Leyburn; Leyburn, Margaret Kerr; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 11)
  In the first letter, Mary writes from Korea to his sister Margaret about a picnice, friensd, gardens, and her husbands missionary work.The second item is only pages 9-12 of a letter written by Mary Junkin Leyburn from Korea.
- Three Undated Letters, 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Letters include:Part of a letter to Alice ("Aunt Alice" is mentioned in William Leyburn's letter to his father and Ann Leyburn in 1839) not signed, about family and friendsLetter written by James to his grandmother, most likely the James who addressed Ann Eliza as "Grandma." He also mentions Alice.A letter to Ann Eliza (before 1837) from a cousin about dress materials she plans to purhcase.
  Leyburn, Ann Eliza
- Magazine Photographs of Jerusalem Engraved for the Youth's Companion (signed by A. E. Leyburn), Craig, W. M.; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Engraving
- U.S. Internal Revenue License granted to John Leyburn to Practice Medicine, 1866-10; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Licenses; Medicine; Leyburn, John
- Manuscript Recipe for Tangled Branches (bread), 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Recipes -- Manuscripts
- French Patent Granted to Edward Leyburn, 1881-01-03; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  The patent was for improvements in hand trucks or barrows. The file includes a "Brevet D'invention" manuscript about this patent, dated Paris, 10 Nov. 1880.
  Patents; Leyburn, Edward J.
- A Brevet D'invention About the French Patent, 1880-11-10; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Grant by Patent Office, London, England, 1880-11-10; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  This file consists of a grant by the Patent Office, London, England, to W. R. Lake of Southampton, for English certificate of a patent for improvement in hand trucks or barrows, patented in U.S.A. and France by Leyburn, with signed statement by Lake of his obtaining this protection.
  Leyburn, Edward J.
- Manuscript Statements by Edward Leyburn Stating that his Attorney Can Dispose of This Patent, 1881-05-25; Leyburn, Edward J.; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  This file consists of three manuscript statements by Edward J. Leyburn, Fredericksburg, Va., stating that Rev. James P. Smith is his attorney and can dispose of this patent for the German empire and United Kingdom. The documents are certified by a notary.
- Junkin Family Tree, 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  This file consists of four typewritten pages labelled "Junkin Family Tree" and of eight pages of family records of marriage, births, and deaths. There is also photocopies of these documents.
  Genealogy; Junkin family
- Newspaper Articles on the Junkin Family, Diehl, George West; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  This file includes four leaves of the newspaper as well as photocopies.
  Newspapers; Junkin family; Junkin, George, 1798 - 1868
- "Leyburn Family" Manuscripts, 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  The manuscripts are acouns of the chief events in the family history. Both of the manuscripts are written in the same hand.
  Manuscripts; Genealogy; Leyburn family
- Alexander Geneology, 1 Item 7 1/4" x 9 1/2" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  This file consists of a notebook containing 113 pages o genealogical notes. There is also an additional 34 pages of manuscript notes on the Caruthers family in a different hand (likely the same hand as the notes on the Leyburn Family in folder 15).
  Genealogy; Alexander family; Caruthers family